Guide to the Alliance for Cultural Democracy Records TAM.832
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Alliance for Cultural Democracy Records
1974-1996, 2024
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Alliance for Cultural Democracy
Branfman, Judy
Cushing, Lincoln, 1953-
Langerman, Deborah
Mikich, Tripp
deNobriga, Kathie
TAM.832
5.5 Linear Feet in 11 manuscript boxes
2 websites in 2 archived websites.
Alliance for Cultural Democracy (ACD) was an activist arts organization active in the 1980s and 1990s. ACD began in December 1976 as the Neighborhood Arts Programs National Organizing Committee (NAPNOC). It grew to include over 150 cultural groups and many cultural workers based in urban, suburban, and rural settings, including muralists, theater people, videographers, craftspeople, musicians, photographers, publishers, organizers, and activists. As federal funding waned, the goals and definition of the organization evolved to encompass a broader vision of what became known as "cultural democracy", the idea that cultural, racial, gender, national, ethnic, and other communities in global society had the right to exert their identities, practices, and arts through cultural, community, and aesthetic expressions at all levels. In 1983 the group changed its name to the Alliance for Cultural Democracy and NAPNOC Notes became Cultural Democracy, which was published on a mostly quarterly basis. In 1993 the organization began to slowly dissolve, formally ending around 1996. The Alliance for Cultural Democracy Records (dated 1974-1996) consists of materials created and collected by the organization as represented by five of its participants and organizers: Judy Branfman, Kathie deNobriga, Tripp Mikich, Deb Langerman, and Lincoln Cushing. Through governance meeting minutes, board documents, correspondence, newsletters, archived websites, policy papers, and conference materials, the collection documents the history of the Neighborhood Arts Programs National Organizing Committee (NAPNOC) as it evolved into the Alliance for Cultural Democracy (ACD), as well as the history of ACD as an organization. The collection also includes correspondence, surveys and other materials sent to members, membership directories, and materials exchanged with, and documentation of, network members around the world. Publications produced by NAPNOC and ACD in this collection include the Cultural Bill of Rights, NAPNOC Notes, Cultural Democracy, and Huracán, as well as regional bulletins. The collection also includes alternative press publications concerning the intersections of art and activism. The materials in this collection document NAPNOC and ACD's activities and mission, as well as the role of arts and culture in building a more just and peaceful world. Other themes include international solidarity, the funding patterns for the arts, and the role of equitable access to cultural expression.
Scope and Contents
The Alliance for Cultural Democracy Records (dated 1974-1996) consists of materials created and collected by the organization as represented by five of its participants and organizers: Judy Branfman, Kathie deNobriga, Tripp Mikich, Deb Langerman, and Lincoln Cushing. Through governance meeting minutes, board documents, correspondence, newsletters, archived websites, policy papers, and conference materials, the collection documents the history of the Neighborhood Arts Programs National Organizing Committee (NAPNOC) as it evolves into the Alliance for Cultural Democracy (ACD), as well as the history of ACD as an organization. The collection also includes correspondence, surveys and other materials sent to members, membership directories, and materials exchanged with, and documentation of, network members around the world. Publications produced by NAPNOC and ACD in this collection include the Cultural Bill of Rights, NAPNOC Notes, Cultural Democracy, and Huracan, as well as regional bulletins. The collection also includes alternative press publications concerning the intersections of art and activism. The materials in this collection document NAPNOC and ACD's activities and mission, as well as the role of arts and culture in building a more just and peaceful world. Other themes include international solidarity, the funding patterns for the arts, and the role of equitable access to cultural expression.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donors.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital surrogates of many issues of ACD publications are available at https://wayback.archive-it.org/22918/*/https://www.docspopuli.org/articles/ACD/ACD.html
Historical Note
Alliance for Cultural Democracy (ACD) was an activist arts organization active in the 1980s and 1990s. ACD began in December 1976 as the Neighborhood Arts Programs National Organizing Committee (NAPNOC). The founding meeting was held at the United Auto Workers' Family Education Center in Black Lake, Michigan, in December 1976, bringing together two dozen community arts activists and allies from all over the country, many of whom had been supported through the Comprehensive Employment and Training Act(CETA). The organizers began publishing a newsletter, NAPNOC Notes, to maintain communication and dialogue. The organization was funded by the Department of Labor from 1977 through 1979. It grew to include over 150 cultural groups and many cultural workers based in urban, suburban, and rural settings, including muralists, theater people, videographers, craftspeople, musicians, photographers, publishers, organizers, and activists. As federal funding waned, the goals and definition of the organization evolved to encompass a broader vision of what became known as "cultural democracy", the idea that cultural, racial, gender, national, ethnic, and other communities in global society had the right to exert their identities, practices, and arts through cultural, community, and aesthetic expressions at all levels. In 1983 the group changed its name to the Alliance for Cultural Democracy and NAPNOC Notes became Cultural Democracy, which was published on a mostly quarterly basis. Its most successful national campaigns were its efforts to promote a "Cultural Bill of Rights," as well as an effort to create an alternative to the 1992 Columbus Quincentennial. This campaign was inspired by the work of Indigenous and other BIPOC organizations in the U.S. and Latin America, and brought together a vast array of political, cultural, and community groups to counter the dominant culture's narrative of the "discovery of the New World" with one of resistance by Indigenous and other communities. ACD members played important roles in infusing cultural activism into organizing efforts around anti-gentrification and Central American solidarity, and also established ties with cultural activists in other countries. In the later 1980s and early 1990s, changing funding patterns for the arts, along with the urgency of the Gulf War and other national and international issues redirected much of ACD members' energy. Additionally, the counter-quincentennial work raised concerns about how the organization addressed LGBTQ+ and BIPOC issues, and several BIPOC Board members resigned. Additionally, after the death of one of the key Board members in 1993 the organization began to slowly dissolve, formally ending around 1996.
Source: This historical note is based on the description of NAPNOC and ACD provided by the donors.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Alliance for Cultural Democracy members Judy Branfman, Lincoln Cushing, Deb Langerman, Tripp Mikich, and Kathie deNobriga in February 2024. Some materials had been contributed to these donors by Arlene Goldbard, Ricardo Levins Morales, and Joe Lambert prior to their transfer to NYU. The accession number associated with this gift is 2024.018.
In April 2024, https://www.docspopuli.org/articles/ACD/ACD.html and https://acdarchives.blogspot.com/ were selected by curator Shannon O'Neill and captured through the use of Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website.The accession number associated with this website is 2024.024.
Art and social action; Art -- Political aspects.; Art -- Social aspects.; Social movements in art.; Cultural pluralism.; Branfman, Judy; Cushing, Lincoln, 1953-; Langerman, Deborah; Mikich, Tripp; deNobriga, Kathie
- NAPNOC Appalachian Arts Consultation, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- NAPNOC Prospectus (Working Files), 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- NAPNOC Communications, Meetings, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- NAPNOC Direct Assistance Recipients, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- NAPNOC Ford Foundation Grant, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- NAPNOC Press, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- NAPNOC NEA Partnership & Miscellany, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- NAPNOC NEA Special Projects – Services To Field, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- NAPNOC Youth Project, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- NAPNOC History, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 10, Box 2, Folder 1)
- NAPNOC Info Requests, 1977-1980 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Naponoc Jobs Paper, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- NAPNOC, 1976-1979 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- NAPNOC Nap Survey, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- NAPNOC Organizing Piece, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- NAPNOC Neighborhood Arts Training Project, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- NAPNOC Personnel/Administrative Policy, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- NAPNOC Program Funding, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- NAPNOC Prop. 13 Notes & Report, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- NAPNOC Special Report: Self-Sufficiency, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- NAPNOC Study Of Neighborhood Arts Movement, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Correspondence On Blues Festival, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Articles By ACDers, 1991-1993 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- ACD Board, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- ACD Info Package, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
- ACD Letters To Members, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- ACD Letters Answered, 1990-1993 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- ACD Paid Members, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- ACD Quincentennial, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Bulk Mail Permit, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Cultural Bill Of Rights, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
- ACD Quincentennial Committee, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Copyright Office, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Mailing Stuff, 1990-1992 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Merchandise Records, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Post Quincentennial, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Survey, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- ACD Correspondence, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- ACD Huracan Inquiries, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- ACD, 1992-1994 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Bay Area ACD, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
- ACD Conference San Francisco, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Conference Promos, 1981-1989 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Membership Directories, 1988-1994 (Box 4, Folder 6-8)
- NAPNOC Organizing Committee, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Brochures -- Quincentennial, General Brochure, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
- Policies And Bylaws, Draft Declaration Cultural Human Rights, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
- NAPNOC and ACD Newsletters, Including Regional Newsletters And Huracán, How To '92, 1980-1996 (Box 4, Folder 13-62, Box 5, Folder 1-11)
- Writings, 1984-1986 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Alternate Roots, 1985-1992 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- ARC: The Rural Arts Newsletter, 1984-1986 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Upfront, 1984-1985 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Voices Of Dissent, Symposium On The Arts As A Force For Social Change, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Theaterwork, 1981-1983 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Directory Of Arts Activism -- "We Will Not Be Disappeared", 1984 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Alliance For Cultural Democracy Membership Directory, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Cultural Correspondence -- "The Art Of Demonstration", 1985 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Deep Dish Public Access Independent Video -- Mailing Lists; A Resource Guide For Grass Roots, Television Producers, Programmers, Activists And Cultural Workers, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Organize, Organizing For Change A Manual For Activists In The 1990s, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- The Independent, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Publications, 1976-1987 (Box 6, Folder 5-7)
- Publications And Ephemera, 1984-1987 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Board Member Lists, 1988-1996 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Board Member Projects, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Board Notes, 1988-1996 (Box 6, Folder 11-13, Box 7, Folder 1-6)
- ACD Notes and Correspondence (Mostly Listserv), 2000-2001 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- ACD Board Correspondence, 1988, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
- ACD Correspondence, 1995-1996 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Bill Stroud, 1990-1993 (Box 7, Folder 10-12)
- ACD Artists Insurance, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 13)
- ACD Business, circa mid-1990s-2000 (Box 7, Folder 14)
- ACD Historical Timeline, 1976-1996 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- ACD Organizational Proposals, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- ACD/NAPNOC By-Laws, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
- ACD Stationary and Brochures, 1986-1996 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Columbus Quincentennial, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Cultural Democracy Submissions, 1991-2001 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Cultural Democracy #43 Manuscripts and Related Materials, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Cultural Democracy #44 Manuscripts and Related Materials, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Cultural Democracy Graphics, 1991-1994 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Cultural Democracy Manuscripts, 1990-1992 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- ACD Associated Groups, Organizations, Actions, 1988-1992 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- ACD International, 1991-1992 (Box 8, Folder 12)
- ACD Mailing Lists, 1986-1990 (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Arts Organizing (Educational), 1991-1996 (Box 8, Folder 14)
- AWOL (Artists And Writers Outloud), 1991 (Box 8, Folder 15)
- Australia ACD, 1990-1996 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Bibliographies, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Listing Services For Cultural Democracy, 1992-1996 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- ACD Brochure, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Resist Newsletter, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- ACD Board Meeting Minutes, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- ACD Briefing Book By President Deborah Langerman, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Paper By Board Member Deborah Langerman: "Cultural Organizing" - 14 Pages, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Conferences, 1986-1992 (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Minutes From March 20, 1988, Boston ACD Meeting (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Declaration Of Cultural Human Rights -- Drafts; Returned Questionnaires; Correspondence Among ACD People; Feedback From Don & Arlene, Another Standard, Ron Sokolsky, & Others; Publications Where It Was Printed; Judy's Notes; Cultural Democracy Focused On Project; A Few Related Articles, 1986-1990 (Box 9, Folder 11)
- British - Jubilee Arts Stories; Letter To/From Docklands 1987; ACD Letter Written In Support Of The Docklands Community; Poster Project In London (Box 9, Folder 12)
- ACD Community Arts Articles, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 13)
- By-Laws; IRS Letters; IRS Incorporation Of Boston Into ACD, 1980-1989 (Box 9, Folder 14)
- Cultural Democracy Issues 18, 35, 36, 39, 40, 1982-1992 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Bulletins -- Midwest, New England, Southeast/Atlanta, Northeast, Northwest, 1978-1990 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- NAPNOC Notes 16, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Huracán: 500 Years Of Resistance, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Stationary, 1986-1990 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- "Community Murals: An International Visual Arts Magazine", 1986 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- "A Border Handbook" By And Two Papers On Los Comadres, A Binational Women Artists' Collective, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- "This Too Is A Political Document: The Description Of The Making Of A Work Of Art, November 12, 1983" By Charles Frederick (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Programs From "Arts In Action" Conference, Boston 1988 (Judy On Planning Committee) (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Judy's Notes, Program, And Schedule For "The Aesthetics Of Community-Based Art Making", 1993 (Box 10, Folder 10)
- 8 Issues Of GAP (Grassroots & Pavements, A National Journal Of Artsin America'S Neighborhoods), 1981-1986 (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Articles, Campaign Update, Pr Photos, On Dewayne Readus' Low-Watt Radio Station In Springfield, Il, Public Housing And The FCC's Efforts To Shut It Down, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 12)
- "Art Education: Building A Contemporar Framework" Course Readings (College Of The Atlantic, Bar Harbor, ME), 1988 (Box 10, Folder 13-15)
- Murals -- Publications, 1974-1980 (Box 10, Folder 16)
- NWICO -- Letters And Articles From/By Colleen Roach About The New World Information Order, 1987-1989 (Box 10, Folder 17)
- International Groups, circa 1980s (Box 10, Folder 18)
- Brit Tour -- Pamphlets, Publications, Articles, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 19)
- Valley & Vale Article, 1986-1988 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- "British Stuff" Collected by Judy Branfman -- Pamphlets, Publications, Ephemera, circa 1980s (Box 11, Folder 2-3)
- Two Syllabus By Ron Sakolsky For "Cultural Democracy Classes (Sagamon State College, Springfield, IL), 1986-1987 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Readings From Ron Sakolsky'S Cultural Democracy Class At Sagamon State College, 1987 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Cultural Policy, circa 1980s (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Coolidge Center, 1985-1986 (Box 11, Folder 7)
- "A Descriptive Study Of Community Arts Teachers With Implications For Teacher Preparation And Cultural Policy" By Rogena M Degge, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Conference Materials; Newsletters; Declaration Of Cultural Human Rights; Governance And Membership, 1982-1994 (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Archived Websites, April 2024
  Appraisal
  Scope was expanded to include blogger.googleusercontent.com to capture images embedded at https://acdarchives.blogspot.com/.
  Scope and Contents
  The websites, maintained by Lincoln Cushing, contain digitized issues of NAPNOC Notes. By issue 17, NAPNOC Notes changed its name to Cultural Democracy. The websites also include an historical reflection by Arlene Goldbard, a digitized membership directory from 1989, and their Declaration of Cultural Human Rights from 1996.